Finding aid to Smith College Medal Committee Records CA.MS.00093
Smith College Archives
Smith College Medal Committee records
1911-2003
Smith College Archives
Smith College. Medal Committee.
CA.MS.00093
14.583 linear feet (33 containers)
The Smith College Medal Committee records consist of minutes of committee meetings, correspondence, press releases, news clippings, memorandums, biographical information on medalists and nominees, nominations forms, letters of recommendation, photographs of medalists and various other papers which document the committee's complicated process of researching possible candidates and selecting medal recipients.
Biographical / Historical
The Smith College Medal was first awarded in November 1964 as a means of honoring the "distinguished service" of alumnae. The Medal is awarded annually to those alumnae, and in exceptional cases, faculty, who "exemplify in their lives and service to the community or the College the true purpose of a liberal arts education."
The Smith College Medal Committee was formed in 1962 to establish the guidelines for awarding the Medal. Composed of faculty, alumnae and members of the College administration appointed by the president, the Smith College Medal Committee meets several times a year to research and present possible candidates and to choose the medal recipients. They also make preparations for the Medal Awards Ceremony held each year at Rally Day (before 1972-73 it was held in October).
Since 1964, the Committee has awarded over 150 Medals to those from a diverse range of interests and fields who have been an outstanding service to their communities and to the College.
Scope and Contents
The Business series consists of material about the medals, committee business, restricted committee files, and committee preparations for the Medal Awards Ceremony. Although the smallest of the five series, it provides a look into the internal workings of the Committee. Included are items concerning the design of the medal itself, statistics on the Medalists, photographs, procedural guides for Committee members, minutes, and meeting notices.
The series also has material about the Committee's preparations for each year's Medal Awards Ceremony. For each year, these papers are divided into general, correspondence, and preparation between the medalists and the Committee. The documents detail the planning process of the event itself.
The Medalists series include a file for each medalist, ordered alphabetically by the name they received the medal under. These files include such items as a medalist's published works, newspaper and magazine clippings, photographs, and other biographical information. The restricted files include letters of recommendation, nomination forms and any other material that mentions names of those who nominated or recommended as a medal recipient.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into five series:
Series I. Business
Series II. Medalists
Series III. Nominees
Series IV. Gloria Whitton Heath medalist
Series V. Other Medalists
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives, with some exceptions. All boxes marked RESTRICTED contain strictly confidential information. They are open only to the College Archivists, the members of the Medal Committee, the President of the College and the Board of Trustees. Medalists may have access to their own confidential file. Confidential materials include: all nominee files, letters of recommendation and nomination forms for medalists, and any Committee document that states the names of nominees.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown
Smith College -- medals; Smith College. Medal Committee.; Smith College--Awards.; Smith College--Alumni and alumnae.
- SERIES I. BUSINESS FILES
  - Medal Design - Baskin (Box 103, Folder 1)
  - Medal Design - Offner (Box 103, Folder 2)
  - General, undated (Box 103, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of groups of medalists (Box 103, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of medal (Box 103, Folder 5)
  - Statistics (Box 103, Folder 6)
  - Business files, 1962-93 (Box 103.1, Folder 1-21)
    General
    RESTRICTED
  - Business files, 1964-98 (Box 103.2, Folder 1-24)
  - Awards Ceremony Preparations
    - General, 1964-65 (Box 103.4, Folder 1)
    - General, 1965-66 (Box 103.4, Folder 2)
    - Preparation, Correspondence, 1965-66 (Box 103.4, Folder 3)
    - General, 1966-67 (Box 103.4, Folder 4)
    - Preparation, 1966-67 (Box 103.4, Folder 5)
    - General, 1967-68 (Box 103.4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1967-68 (Box 103.4, Folder 7)
    - Preparation, 1968-69 (Box 103.4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1968-69 (Box 103.4, Folder 9)
    - Preparation, 1968-69 (Box 103.4, Folder 10)
    - General, 1969-70 (Box 103.4, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1969-70 (Box 103.4, Folder 12)
    - Preparation, 1969-70 (Box 103.4, Folder 13)
    - General, 1970-71 (Box 103.4, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1970-71 (Box 103.4, Folder 15)
    - Preparation, 1970-71 (Box 103.4, Folder 16)
    - General, 1971-72 (Box 103.4, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1971-72 (Box 103.4, Folder 18)
    - Preparation, 1971-72 (Box 103.4, Folder 19)
    - General, 1972-73 (Box 103.4, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1972-73 (Box 103.4, Folder 21)
    - Preparation, 1972-73 (Box 103.4, Folder 22)
    - General, 1973-74 (Box 103.4, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1973-74 (Box 103.4, Folder 24)
    - Preparation, 1973-74 (Box 103.4, Folder 25)
    - General, Correspondence, 1974-75 (Box 103.4, Folder 26)
    - General, 1975-76 (Box 103.4, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence, 1975-76 (Box 103.4, Folder 28)
    - Preparation, 1975-76 (Box 103.4, Folder 29)
    - General, 1976-77 (Box 103.4, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence, 1976-77 (Box 103.4, Folder 31)
    - Preparation, 1976-77 (Box 103.4, Folder 32)
    - General, 1977-78 (Box 103.5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1977-78 (Box 103.5, Folder 2)
    - Preparation, 1977-78 (Box 103.5, Folder 3)
    - General, 1978-79 (Box 103.5, Folder 4)
    - Preparation, 1978-79 (Box 103.5, Folder 5)
    - General, 1979-80 (Box 103.5, Folder 6)
    - General, 1980-81 (Box 103.5, Folder 7)
    - General, 1981-82 (Box 103.5, Folder 8)
    - General, 1982-83 (Box 103.5, Folder 9)
    - General, 1983-84 (Box 103.5, Folder 10)
    - General, 1984-85 (Box 103.5, Folder 11)
    - General, 1985-86 (Box 103.5, Folder 12)
    - General, 1986-87 (Box 103.5, Folder 13)
    - General, 1987-88 (Box 103.5, Folder 14)
    - General, 1988-89 (Box 103.5, Folder 15)
    - General, 1989-90 (Box 103.5, Folder 16)
    - Preparation, 1990-91 (Box 103.5, Folder 17)
    - Preparation, Correspondence, 1991-92 (Box 103.5, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1992-93 (Box 103.5, Folder 19)
    - Preparation, 1992-93 (Box 103.5, Folder 20)
    - General, 1994-95 (Box 103.5, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1995-96 (Box 103.5, Folder 22)
    - General, Correspondence, 1997-98 (Box 103.5, Folder 23)
- SERIES II. MEDALISTS
  - Adachi, Barbara Curtis 1945, 1986 (Box 104)
  - Adams, Aileen 1966, 1993 (Box 104)
  - Addiss, Susan Silliman Tracy 1951, 1981 (Box 104)
  - Allensworth, Dorothy Etzensperger 1929, 1980 (Box 104)
  - Altschul, Marylin Bender 1944, 1978 (Box 104)
  - Andersen, Margret Booth 1946, 1979 (Box 104)
  - Babbott, Joan Griggs 1948, 1994 (Box 104)
  - Bailey, Ethel Z. 1911, 1970 (Box 104)
  - Bank, Mirra 1967, 1970 (Box 104)
  - Bates, Barbara 1949, 1990 (Box 104)
  - Bates, Janet MacDonald 1937, 1988 (Box 104)
  - Bauman, Margaret Lang 1960, 1988 (Box 104)
  - Bennett, Margaret Goldthwait 1921, 1969 (Box 104)
  - Benson, Lucy Wilson 1949, 1969 (Box 104)
  - Beshar, Christine von Wedemeyer 1953, 1974 (Box 104)
  - Bing, Lucia Johnson 1906, 1964 (Box 104)
  - Bissell, Nancy Keebler 1961, 1991 (Box 104)
  - Blum, Priscilla Haas 1946, 1989 (Box 104)
  - Bodden, William, 1965 (Box 104)
  - Bornholdt, Laura 1940, 1987 (Box 104)
  - Borton, Nan Darling 1962, 1994 (Box 104)
  - Bourne, Dorothy Dulles 1915, 1968 (Box 104)
  - Brinckerhoff, Constance, 1963 (Box 104)
  - Brown, Janet Welsh, 1953 (Box 104)
  - Burack, Sylvia Kamerman 1938, 1995 (Box 104)
  - Campbell, William I.P., 1978 (Box 104.1)
  - Chacko, Dorothy Dunning 1925, 1970 (Box 104.1)
  - Chase, Julia 1964, 1986 (Box 104.1)
    CLOSED
  - Chester, Ruth 1914, 1966 (Box 104.1)
  - Child, Julia McWilliams 1934, 1969 (Box 104.1)
  - Clark, Eleanor MSS 1951, 1965 (Box 104.1)
  - Chess, Stella 1935, 1999 (Box 104.1)
  - Chun, Dora 1938, 1981 (Box 104.1)
  - Cohen, Joan Lebold 1954, 1990 (Box 104.1)
  - Conover, Anne Rudolph 1928, 1977 (Box 104.1)
  - Consagra, Sophie Chandler 1949, 1986 (Box 104.1)
  - Corkin, Suzanne Hammond 1959, 1995 (Box 104.1)
  - Curtis, Lucille Atcherson 1913, 1980 (Box 104.1)
  - Dale, Madeline McWhinney 1943, 1971 (Box 104.1)
  - Dalrymple, Bernice Barber 1910, 1969 (Box 104.1)
  - Darrow, Louise de Schweinitz 1918, 1981 (Box 104.1)
    see also separate box
  - Davinroy, Claire 1973, posthumously (Box 104.1)
  - Davis, Natalie Zemon 1949, 1996 (Box 104.1)
  - de Schweinitz, Dorothea 1912, 1974 (Box 104.1)
    CLOSED, see also finding aid
  - Desmond, Murdina MacFarquhar 1938, 1993 (Box 104.1)
  - Diamond, Liebe Sokol 1951, 1996 (Box 104.1)
  - Dillon, Joan Kent 1947, 1993 (Box 104.1)
  - Fanning, Katherine Woodruff 1949, 1980 (Box 104.2)
  - Farenthold, Sally Curtis 1959, 1988 (Box 104.2)
  - Fish, Marie Poland 1921, 1964 (Box 104.2)
  - Fogg, Helen Louise 1924, 1964 (Box 104.2)
  - Frantz, M. Alison 1924, 1967 (Box 104.2)
  - Galvin, Ruth B. Mehrtens 1942, 1974 (Box 104.2)
  - Gatov, Elizabeth Rudel 1933, 1988 (Box 104.2)
  - Giffin, Mary Elizabeth 1939, 1978 (Box 104.2)
  - Glover, Virginia Dougherty 1942, 1976 (Box 104.2)
  - Golden, Thelma 1987, 1997 (Box 104.2)
    NO FILE
  - Goodwin, Dorothy C. 1937, 1984 (Box 104.2)
  - Grierson, Margaret Storrs 1922, 1968 (Box 104.2)
  - Gulliver, Adelaide Cromwell 1940, 1971 (Box 104.2)
  - Hakim, Joy 1951, 1999 (Box 104.2)
  - Harpur, Eleanor MacKenzie 1934, 1969 (Box 104.2)
  - Haseltine, Miriam 1916, 1971 (Box 104.2)
    see also separate boxes
  - Heath, Gloria Whitton 1943, 1971 (Box 104.2)
  - Hiatt, Iva Dee, 1979 (Box 104.2)
    no file, see also finding aid
  - Hill, Helen Zimmerman 1950, 1997 (Box 104.2)
  - Hirsch, Hortense Mayer 1907, 1968 (Box 104.2)
  - Hirschberg, Nell 1928, 1978 (Box 104.2)
  - Hodgkinson, Laura Cabot 1922, 1965 (Box 104.2)
  - Holmberg, Ruth Sulzberer 1943, 1988 (Box 104.2)
  - Howard, Katherine Graham 1920, 1967 (Box 104.2)
  - Hoyt, Nelly Schargo 1943, 1989 (Box 104.2)
    no file, see finding aid
  - Ikeda, Sue Yung Li 1955, 1983 (Box 104.2)
  - Isaacs, Marion Scranton 1930, 1978 (Box 104.2)
  - Jamison, Marjorie Carr 1909, 1966 (Box 104.2)
  - Kahn, Louise Wolff 1931, 1987 (Box 104.2)
  - Kaminer, Wendy 1971, 1998 (Box 104.2)
  - Kelley, Peggy Clark 1935, 1977 (Box 104.2)
  - Kilgore, Emilie Smith 1957, 1995 (Box 104.2)
  - King, Carolyn Dineen 1959, 1997 (Box 104.2)
  - Lappas, Alexandra 1960, 1979 (Box 104.3)
  - L'Engle, Madeleine 1941, 1981
  - Levine, Rhea Cotter 1960, 1994
  - Lippard, Lucy 1958, 1992
  - Lucas, Elizabeth Low 1917, 1971
  - MacClintock, Dorcas Easton 1954, 1987
  - MacKinnon, Catharine 1969, 1991
  - Mayer, Hortense Brigham 1951, 1984
  - McMenamin, Joan Stitt 1946, 1985
  - Means, Helen Hotchkin 1919, 1981
  - Mellon, Gwen Grant 1934, 1997
    OPEN FILE
  - Mendenhall, Cornelia Baker no file, 1975
  - Miner, Francis 1927, 1964
  - Miller, Lynden Breed 1960, 1995
  - Miller, Pamela Gundersen 1960, 1998
  - Moldow, Susan 1967, 2003
  - Molthan, Marian 1949, 1987
  - Moore, Eudorah Morse 1940, 1973
  - Morgan, Constance Morrow 1935, S 1974
  - Morse, Meroe Marston 1945, 1968
  - Mosee, Lillian B. Witten 1918, 1974
  - Moss, Cynthia 1962, 1985
  - Munro, Eleanor 1949, 1994
  - Oakes, Helen Baum 1945, 1991
  - Oberlander, Cornelia Hahn 1944, 1982
  - Peabody, Francis Wilson 1925, 1992 (Box 104.4)
  - Pell, Mary Chase 1937, 1993 (Box 104.4)
  - Perkins, Emelie Munson 1910, 1977 (Box 104.4)
  - Phelps, Edith Blakeslee 1938, 1971 (Box 104.4)
  - Picker, Jean Sovatkin 1942, 1977 (Box 104.4)
  - Porter, Barbara Cooney 1938, 1976 (Box 104.4)
  - Poole, Joyce H. 1979, 1996 (Box 104.4)
  - Pyle, Alice Parker 1947, 1982 (Box 104.4)
  - Read, Helen Appleton 1908, 1968 (Box 104.4)
  - Reed, Glenda Copes 1966, 1982 (Box 104.4)
  - Reid, M. Lucile 1967, 2003 (Box 104.4)
  - Rich, Francis Luther 1931, 1973 (Box 104.4)
  - Riger, Eleanor Sanger 1950, 1982 (Box 104.4)
  - Rityo, Miriam Meyers 1937, 1991 (Box 104.4)
  - Roberts, Mary Gordon 1960, 1985 (Box 104.4)
  - Ronk, Sally Stewat 1934, 1979 (Box 104.4)
  - Rozendaal, Katherine Scranton 1931, 1986 (Box 104.4)
    no file
  - Sammartino, Sylvia Scaramelli 1925, 1967 (Box 104.4)
  - Sanger, Eleanor, 1950 (Box 104.4)
    see Riger, Eleanor Sanger 1950
  - Schafran, Lynn Hecht 1962, 1992 (Box 104.4)
  - Schwartz, Felice Nierenberg 1946, 1976 (Box 104.4)
  - Shipley, Elizabeth McCard 1928, 1990 (Box 104.4)
  - Siegel, Joyce Bernhard 1955, 1970 (Box 104.4)
  - Sivard, Ruth Leger 1937, 1985 (Box 104.4)
  - Skogland, Sandra 1968, 2003 (Box 104.4)
  - Smith, Alice Orme 1911, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Smith, Marilyn Ray 1965, 2003 (Box 11)
  - Solomon, Maida Herman 1912, 1979 (Box 11)
  - Stage, Elizabeth K. 1972, 1996 (Box 11)
  - Stanton, Madeline Earle 1919, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Stella, Gertrude Ridgeway 1937, May 1981 (Box 11)
  - Stern, Joanne Melniker 1944, 1983 (Box 11)
  - Sterne, Dorah Heyman 1919, 1985 (Box 11)
  - Stevenson, Ferdinan Nancy Backer 1949, 1984 (Box 11)
  - Straus, Ellen Sulzberger 1946, 1971 (Box 11)
  - Strickland, Katherine Gabel 1959, 1976 (Box 11)
  - Tangeman, Clementine Miller 1927, 1967 (Box 11)
  - Taylor, Juliet 1967, 1990 (Box 11)
  - Thacher, Gladys Stevens 1950, 1992 (Box 11)
  - Thompson, Margaret Cook 1911, 1965 (Box 11)
  - Thompson, Mary Rines 1940, May 1981 (Box 11)
  - Thompson, Myrtle Fish 1992, 1966 (Box 11)
  - Tippie, Virginia 1972, 1999 (Box 11)
  - Toy, Pearl Tak-Chu Yau 1969, 1991 (Box 11)
  - Treuhaft, Elizabeth Marting 1926, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Tyson, Laura D'Andrea 1969, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Valentine, Joan Selverstone 1967, 1991 (Box 11)
  - Wallace, Jane House Wallace 1947, 1992 (Box 104.6)
  - Walmsley, Dorothy Hamilton 1917, 1967 (Box 104.6)
  - Washburn, Barbara Polk 1935, 1980 (Box 104.6)
  - Webster, Kate Belcher 1946, 1982 (Box 104.6)
  - Weil, Gertrude 1901, 1964 (Box 104.6)
  - Weldon, Virginia Verral 1957, 1984 (Box 104.6)
  - Weltman, Esther Ziskind 1922, 1976 (Box 104.6)
  - Will, Madeline Marion 1967, 1989 (Box 104.6)
  - Winchester, Alice 1929, 1968 (Box 104.6)
  - Wing, Virginia 1945 no file, 1989 (Box 104.6)
  - Wintersteen, Bernice McIlhenny 1945, May 1981 (Box 104.6)
  - Wright, Jane 1942, 1968 (Box 104.6)
  - Wright, Katharyn Stubbs 1935, 1970 (Box 104.6)
  - Yang, Caroline Matano 1958, 1989 (Box 104.6)
  - Yolen, Jane 1960, 1990 (Box 104.6)
  - Medalists A-Bl (Box 104.7)
    (RESTRICTED)
  - Medalists Bo-C (Box 104.8)
  - Medalists D-Ha (Box 104.9)
  - Medalists He-Le (Box 104.10)
  - Medalists Li-Pe (Box 104.11)
  - Medalists Ph-S (Box 104.12)
  - Medalists T-Z (Box 104.13)
- SERIES III. NOMINEES
  - Nominees A-D (Box 105)
  - Nominees E-J (Box 105.1)
  - Nominees K-M (Box 105.2)
  - Nominees Mo-Sm (Box 106)
  - Nominees Sn-Z (Box 106.1)
- SERIES IV. MIRIAM WOODS HASELTINE (1971-72 Medalist)
  - A-B (Box 107)
  - Correspondence, 1912-1915 (Box 108)
  - E-P (Box 109)
  - Photographs, Scrapbook (Box 110)
  - Correspondence R-Z, 1915-1960 (Box 111)
- SERIES V. OTHER MEDALISTS, 1911-1981
  - Alice Orne Smith 1911 (1972-73 Medalist) biographical information, landscape design photos and WWI scrapbooks (Box 118)
  - Madeline Earle Stanton 1919 (1972-73 medalist) (Box 119)
  - Nell Hirschberg 1928 (1977-78 medalist) (Box 120)
  - Louise de Schweinitz Darrow 1918(1980-81 medalist) biographical information (Box 121)